<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://lakhwinder.co/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://lakhwinder.co/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-19T19:59:02+05:30</updated><id>https://lakhwinder.co/atom.xml</id><title type="html">Lakhwinder Singh</title><subtitle>Personal Blog and Portfolio</subtitle><author><name>Lakhwinder Singh</name><email>lakhwinder.code@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Web3 Week</title><link href="https://lakhwinder.co/2023/09/11/web3-week/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Web3 Week" /><published>2023-09-11T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-09-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://lakhwinder.co/2023/09/11/web3-week</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lakhwinder.co/2023/09/11/web3-week/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="exploring-web3-my-journey-through-web3-week">Exploring Web3: My Journey Through Web3 Week</h1>

<p>Last week, I had the opportunity to dive deep into the world of Web3 during the Web3 Week hosted by the MLH community. It was an exhilarating experience filled with learning, coding, and exploration of the decentralized web. Here’s a recap of the hacks I was a part of and the valuable lessons I learned along the way:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/files/web3.webp" alt="web3" /></p>

<h2 id="1-basic-smart-contract">1. Basic Smart Contract:</h2>
<p>Our journey into Web3 started with building our very first smart contract using Solidity on Codedamn’s online editor. This simple yet foundational project taught me the basics of Ethereum Virtual Machine (EVM), gas, and smart contracts. By following the FreeCodeCamp tutorial, I gained insights into Solidity development and successfully deployed our contract on the Sepolia/Goerli testnet. This laid the groundwork for further exploration into blockchain development.</p>

<p><strong>Key Learnings:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Understanding of EVM and gas in Ethereum transactions</li>
  <li>Introduction to Solidity programming language</li>
  <li>Deployment of smart contracts on testnets</li>
  <li>Familiarization with Solidity development environment</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://devpost.com/software/basic-smart-contract?ref_content=user-portfolio&amp;ref_feature=in_progress">Basic Smart Contract on Devpost</a></p>

<h2 id="2-programmable-wallet-using-circles-web3-services">2. Programmable Wallet using Circle’s Web3 Services:</h2>
<p>Next, we delved into the realm of programmable wallets with Circle’s Web3 API. Through RESTful APIs in Python, we learned how to store digital cryptocurrencies and facilitate wallet-to-wallet transactions. Despite facing challenges with fetching data from Circle Web3 APIs, we successfully transferred MATIC to a digital wallet, marking a significant accomplishment in our Web3 journey.</p>

<p><strong>Key Learnings:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Utilization of RESTful APIs in Python</li>
  <li>Setting up and working with programmable wallets using Circle’s Web3 API</li>
  <li>Hands-on experience with Linux-based Curl</li>
  <li>Conducting wallet-to-wallet transactions and managing blockchain assets</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://devpost.com/software/programmable-wallet-using-circle-s-web3-services?ref_content=user-portfolio&amp;ref_feature=in_progress">Programmable Wallet using Circle’s Web3 Services on Devpost</a></p>

<h2 id="3-hedera-dapp">3. Hedera dapp:</h2>
<p>Our exploration of Web3 culminated with the development of a decentralized app (dapp) utilizing Hedera JavaScript Hashgraph SDK. This project allowed us to perform basic transactions on the Hedera blockchain, including fund transfers between accounts. Despite encountering challenges with private key decoding, we overcame obstacles and successfully completed the project, laying the groundwork for future dapp development on the Hedera blockchain.</p>

<p><strong>Key Learnings:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Setup of testnet accounts and generation of accounts programmatically</li>
  <li>Fundamentals of transaction processing on the Hedera blockchain</li>
  <li>Troubleshooting and debugging blockchain-related issues</li>
  <li>Completion of a functional dapp utilizing Hedera blockchain</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://devpost.com/software/hedera-dapp-ny389u?ref_content=user-portfolio&amp;ref_feature=in_progress">Hedera dapp on Devpost</a></p>

<h2 id="4-web3-apis-challenge">4. Web3 APIs Challenge:</h2>
<p>In this challenge, we explored Moralis Web3 Wallet API to fetch account balances on different blockchain networks. Utilizing Python, we interacted with the Wallet API to access multi-chain activity of an account address. This involved signing up for Moralis, creating a project, and utilizing the secret API key provided by Moralis. Through this challenge, we gained insights into Moralis Web3 API and the usage of APIs in general.</p>

<p><strong>Key Learnings:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Understanding of Moralis Web3 API</li>
  <li>Practical usage of APIs in fetching blockchain data</li>
  <li>Integration possibilities for multi-chain functionality into existing projects</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://devpost.com/software/web3-apis-challenge?ref_content=user-portfolio&amp;ref_feature=in_progress">Web3 APIs Challenge on Devpost</a></p>

<h2 id="5-nft-creation">5. NFT Creation:</h2>
<p>Lastly, we explored the creation of non-fungible tokens (NFTs) using the OpenSea marketplace and Metamask wallet. With the rising popularity of NFTs, we embarked on a journey to create our first NFTs, including artwork and project logos. Through this experience, we gained insights into using AI tools for digital art creation, setting up Metamask Wallet, and minting NFTs on the OpenSea marketplace.</p>

<p><strong>Key Learnings:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Utilization of AI tools for digital art creation</li>
  <li>Setup and usage of Metamask Wallet for interacting with NFT marketplaces</li>
  <li>NFT minting process on the OpenSea marketplace</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://devpost.com/software/nft-creation?ref_content=user-portfolio&amp;ref_feature=in_progress">NFT Creation on Devpost</a></p>

<p>With each hackathon, I gained valuable insights and hands-on experience in the rapidly evolving landscape of Web3 technologies. I look forward to continuing my journey and exploring new possibilities in the decentralized web. Stay tuned for more updates and insights from my exploration of Web3!</p>]]></content><author><name>Lakhwinder Singh</name><email>lakhwinder.code@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring Web3: My Journey Through Web3 Week]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">META Certified</title><link href="https://lakhwinder.co/2023/06/06/meta-certification/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="META Certified" /><published>2023-06-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-06-06T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://lakhwinder.co/2023/06/06/meta-certification</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lakhwinder.co/2023/06/06/meta-certification/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="celebrating-achievement-completing-the-meta-front-end-developer-certificate">Celebrating Achievement: Completing the Meta Front-End Developer Certificate</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/files/meta.png" alt="meta_badge" /></p>

<p>I am thrilled to announce that I have successfully completed all nine courses offered by Meta for gaining frontend developer skills. This accomplishment culminates in earning the prestigious Meta Front-End Developer Certificate, issued by Coursera and authorized by Meta.</p>

<h2 id="meta-front-end-developer-certificate-overview">Meta Front-End Developer Certificate Overview:</h2>
<p>The Meta Front-End Developer Certificate is awarded to learners who complete a series of courses on front-end web development, hosted by Coursera. Developed by Meta experts, these rigorous, self-paced courses are designed to prepare candidates for entry-level positions as front-end developers. The curriculum focuses on essential skills such as CSS, HTML, JavaScript ES6, React.js, version control, wireframes, and coding interview skills. The program also includes practical training in editing images to enhance web design projects.</p>

<h2 id="skills-acquired">Skills Acquired:</h2>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Coding Interview Skills:</strong> Prepared for technical interviews with confidence.</li>
  <li><strong>CSS:</strong> Mastered the art of styling web pages with CSS.</li>
  <li><strong>Editing Images:</strong> Acquired skills to edit and optimize images for web usage.</li>
  <li><strong>HTML:</strong> Developed proficiency in structuring web content with HTML.</li>
  <li><strong>JavaScript ES6:</strong> Gained advanced knowledge of JavaScript ES6 features and functionalities.</li>
  <li><strong>React.js:</strong> Learned to build interactive user interfaces using the React.js library.</li>
  <li><strong>Version Control:</strong> Utilized version control systems for efficient project management.</li>
  <li><strong>Wireframes:</strong> Created wireframes to visualize and plan web layouts effectively.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="capstone-project">Capstone Project:</h2>
<p>The journey towards completing the Meta Front-End Developer Certificate culminated in the successful execution of a capstone project. This project served as a comprehensive demonstration of the skills and knowledge acquired throughout the program. Through the capstone project, I was able to showcase my proficiency in front-end development and apply industry best practices to real-world scenarios.</p>

<h2 id="reflection">Reflection:</h2>
<p>Completing the Meta Front-End Developer Certificate has been an enriching experience filled with learning, challenges, and growth. Each course equipped me with valuable insights and practical skills that are essential for a successful career in front-end development. From mastering fundamental concepts to delving into advanced topics like React.js, I am proud of the progress I have made and excited about the opportunities that lie ahead.</p>

<h2 id="next-steps">Next Steps:</h2>
<p>As I celebrate this achievement, I am eager to leverage my newfound skills and knowledge to pursue exciting opportunities in the field of front-end development. I look forward to applying my expertise to contribute to innovative projects, collaborate with talented professionals, and continue my journey of lifelong learning in the ever-evolving landscape of web development.</p>

<p>Stay tuned for more updates and insights as I embark on the next chapter of my journey as a front-end developer!</p>

<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.credly.com/badges/3c642daa-361f-4ecf-95e2-c700fa5bd6da/public_url">Credly - Meta Front-End Developer Certificate</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Lakhwinder Singh</name><email>lakhwinder.code@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Celebrating Achievement: Completing the Meta Front-End Developer Certificate]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hacktoberfest</title><link href="https://lakhwinder.co/2022/10/01/hacktoberfest/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hacktoberfest" /><published>2022-10-01T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-10-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://lakhwinder.co/2022/10/01/hacktoberfest</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lakhwinder.co/2022/10/01/hacktoberfest/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="reflecting-on-hacktoberfest-2022-a-journey-of-collaboration-and-contribution">Reflecting on Hacktoberfest 2022: A Journey of Collaboration and Contribution</h1>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction:</h2>
<p>Hacktoberfest 2022 was a month-long celebration of open source software and community collaboration. It brought together developers from around the world to contribute to meaningful projects, learn new skills, and connect with like-minded individuals. As a participant in this year’s event, I had the opportunity to immerse myself in the vibrant open source community, make valuable contributions, and grow as a developer.</p>

<h2 id="the-spirit-of-hacktoberfest">The Spirit of Hacktoberfest:</h2>
<p>At its core, Hacktoberfest is about more than just writing code. It’s about fostering an inclusive and welcoming environment where developers of all skill levels can come together to make a difference. Whether it’s fixing a bug, adding a feature, or improving documentation, every contribution, no matter how small, plays a part in advancing open source software and making technology more accessible to everyone.</p>

<h2 id="my-journey">My Journey:</h2>
<p>Participating in Hacktoberfest was an enriching experience that allowed me to expand my horizons and challenge myself in new ways. From exploring new programming languages to collaborating with developers from diverse backgrounds, each contribution was an opportunity for growth and learning. Whether it was submitting pull requests, reviewing code, or engaging in discussions, every interaction was a chance to make a positive impact on the open source community.</p>

<h2 id="highlights-and-achievements">Highlights and Achievements:</h2>
<p>Throughout the month, I had the privilege of working on a variety of projects, each with its own unique challenges and rewards. From fixing bugs and implementing new features to improving documentation and accessibility, every contribution was a step forward in my journey as a developer. Some of the highlights include:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Collaborating with experienced developers to address critical issues and improve the overall quality of projects.</li>
  <li>Learning new technologies and best practices through hands-on experience and mentorship from the community.</li>
  <li>Connecting with like-minded individuals through online forums, workshops, and virtual meetups, fostering meaningful relationships and lasting friendships.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="lessons-learned">Lessons Learned:</h2>
<p>Hacktoberfest was not only an opportunity to contribute to open source projects but also a chance to reflect on the importance of collaboration, community, and giving back. It taught me the value of teamwork, communication, and perseverance in overcoming challenges and achieving common goals. It also reinforced the idea that technology has the power to bring people together and drive positive change in the world.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion:</h2>
<p>As I look back on my journey through Hacktoberfest 2022, I am filled with gratitude for the opportunities it provided and the lessons it taught me. It was more than just a month of coding; it was a celebration of creativity, curiosity, and camaraderie. I am proud to have been a part of this global movement, and I look forward to continuing my journey as a contributor to open source software and a member of the vibrant developer community.</p>

<h2 id="swag-and-memorabilia">Swag and Memorabilia:</h2>
<p>In addition to the rewarding experience of contributing to open source, I also received some exciting swag as part of Hacktoberfest 2022. This was my first time receiving stickers, and I was thrilled to add them to my collection. Additionally, I proudly wore the Hacktoberfest T-shirt, a symbol of my participation in this impactful event.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/files/hacktoberfest0.jpg" alt="swag1" />
<img src="/assets/files/hacktoberfest1.jpg" alt="swag1" />
<img src="/assets/files/hacktoberfest2.jpg" alt="swag1" />
<img src="/assets/files/hacktoberfest3.jpg" alt="swag1" /></p>

<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://hacktoberfest.digitalocean.com/">Hacktoberfest Official Website</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/topics/hacktoberfest">Hacktoberfest on GitHub</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://twitter.com/hacktoberfest">Hacktoberfest on Twitter</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Lakhwinder Singh</name><email>lakhwinder.code@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflecting on Hacktoberfest 2022: A Journey of Collaboration and Contribution]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winner in IMPACT Category</title><link href="https://lakhwinder.co/2022/09/02/won-hackathon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winner in IMPACT Category" /><published>2022-09-02T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-09-02T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://lakhwinder.co/2022/09/02/won-hackathon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lakhwinder.co/2022/09/02/won-hackathon/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="winning-the-impact-category-reflecting-on-emerride---our-solution-for-emergency-medical-services">Winning the IMPACT Category: Reflecting on Emerride - Our Solution for Emergency Medical Services</h1>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>I am excited to share that our team emerged victorious in the IMPACT category at an online hackathon with our innovative project, Emerride. The hackathon provided us with a platform to address critical issues in the medical industry, particularly concerning emergency medical services, in light of the challenges posed by the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>

<h2 id="inspiration">Inspiration</h2>
<p>The devastating impact of the COVID-19 pandemic underscored the urgent need for improved awareness, planning, training, and access to medical resources. Our inspiration for Emerride stemmed from the realization of the challenges faced by patients during emergency situations, particularly in India. We identified gaps in access to timely medical assistance and sought to bridge them through technology.</p>

<h2 id="what-emerride-does">What Emerride Does</h2>
<p>Emerride is a comprehensive solution designed to streamline emergency medical services and facilitate access to timely care. Here’s an overview of its key features:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Nearest Ambulance Locator:</strong> Quickly identifies the nearest ambulance for emergency medical services, ensuring swift response times.</li>
  <li><strong>Insurance Verification:</strong> Simplifies the insurance process by checking insurance coverage and facilitating seamless transactions.</li>
  <li><strong>First Aid Tutorials:</strong> Provides essential first aid tutorials to empower individuals to administer basic medical procedures during the critical golden hour.</li>
  <li><strong>Alternative Transport Booking:</strong> Offers the option to book alternative transport options to meet up with the ambulance midway and reach the hospital faster.</li>
  <li><strong>Doctor’s Appointment Scheduling:</strong> Enables users to schedule cabs for doctor’s appointments, ensuring timely access to healthcare services.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="how-we-built-it">How We Built It</h2>
<ul>
  <li><strong>UI/UX Design:</strong> Leveraged FIGMA to design the intuitive user interface and user experience of the Emerride app.</li>
  <li><strong>Development:</strong> Utilized React Native to develop the app, ensuring cross-platform compatibility and seamless performance.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="challenges-faced">Challenges Faced</h2>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Brainstorming:</strong> Navigating through various use cases and scenarios to address in the app posed a significant challenge during the ideation phase.</li>
  <li><strong>Team Management:</strong> Organizing tasks and coordinating efforts among team members required effective team management skills.</li>
  <li><strong>Time Constraints:</strong> Limited time and resources posed challenges in completing development tasks, leading to pending features.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="accomplishments">Accomplishments</h2>
<p>Despite the challenges encountered, we take pride in the following accomplishments:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Successfully completing the UI/UX design of the app, integrating various use cases and solutions effectively.</li>
  <li>Developing the Emerride app using React Native, demonstrating our technical prowess and problem-solving abilities.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="lessons-learned">Lessons Learned</h2>
<p>Participating in the development of Emerride taught us invaluable lessons, including:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Effective team management and collaboration skills.</li>
  <li>Out-of-the-box thinking to address complex challenges.</li>
  <li>Proficiency in UI/UX design using FIGMA and mobile app development with React Native.</li>
  <li>Exploration of APIs for enhanced functionality and integration.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="whats-next-for-emerride">What’s Next for Emerride</h2>
<p>Our journey with Emerride does not end here. Moving forward, we plan to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Further refine and develop the app to address identified loopholes and enhance functionality.</li>
  <li>Incorporate features such as real-time tracking of ambulances using Google Maps API and alternative transport options through the Uber API.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="built-with">Built With</h2>
<ul>
  <li>FIGMA</li>
  <li>Google Maps API</li>
  <li>React Native</li>
  <li>Uber API</li>
  <li>UI/UX Design Principles</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://devpost.com/software/emerride">Check out Emerride on Devpost</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Lakhwinder Singh</name><email>lakhwinder.code@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Winning the IMPACT Category: Reflecting on Emerride - Our Solution for Emergency Medical Services]]></summary></entry></feed>